<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Syntax Sugar</title>
    <link>https://syntaxsugar.de/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Syntax Sugar</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 14 Nov 2017 15:56:05 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://syntaxsugar.de/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Clion Libraries</title>
      <link>https://syntaxsugar.de/posts/clion-libraries/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Nov 2017 15:56:05 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://syntaxsugar.de/posts/clion-libraries/</guid>
      <description>CLion is my preferred C++ IDE. For my Master&amp;rsquo;s thesis, today I had to implement the calculation of Shapley&amp;rsquo;s value - a concept from game theory.
I thought, okay, let&amp;rsquo;s do this properly. I&amp;rsquo;ll be using the calculation inside a simulator, but I want to implement it outside the scope of this huge code framework, so that I can run easily unit-test it. So I&amp;rsquo;ll use CLion and let it compile a library.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>OMNeT&#43;&#43; and INET Simulator Setup</title>
      <link>https://syntaxsugar.de/posts/omnet-setup/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Oct 2017 10:51:10 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://syntaxsugar.de/posts/omnet-setup/</guid>
      <description>I use the popular, modular OMNeT++ simulator for network simulation. The INET Framework adds lots of useful wired, wireless and mobile communication protocols and entities to the simulator.
It turns out many people have problems compiling the two. So I&amp;rsquo;d like to give a quick introduction into how I got them working.
I use OMNeT++ 5.1.1 together with INET 3.5. Both have newer versions, but another framework I use - simuLTE - requires these versions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Building an AUR package with invalid MD5Checksum</title>
      <link>https://syntaxsugar.de/posts/makepkg/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Oct 2017 10:28:28 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://syntaxsugar.de/posts/makepkg/</guid>
      <description>I had an annoying problem: for the simulator I use for research I needed a specific library, as the simulator uses it.
This specific library osgearth is available in the Arch Linux&amp;rsquo;s AUR, but the package maintainer put a wrong MD5 Checksum into the PKGBUILD. Let&amp;rsquo;s say we trust the maintainer and don&amp;rsquo;t believe someone tinkered with the files. What do you do?
Go to an arbitrary directory
cd ~/Download mkdir osgearth cd osgearth  Download the Snapshot from the AUR which should contain the PKGBUILD; extract it from the archive file.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Controlling a display based on a PIR motion detector</title>
      <link>https://syntaxsugar.de/posts/raspi-pir/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 May 2017 15:09:23 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://syntaxsugar.de/posts/raspi-pir/</guid>
      <description>I am working on a Magic Mirror: that&amp;rsquo;s an old LCD display behind a two-way mirror. The mirror shows your reflection when you look at it, but all light coming from behind it passes through - so stuff displayed on the LCD appears on the mirror. A Raspberry Pi 3 controls what is shown using this open source modular smart mirror platform.
Of course I don&amp;rsquo;t want the display to be always on - that&amp;rsquo;d be bad for my electricity bill.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Simulation evaluation in OMNeT&#43;&#43;</title>
      <link>https://syntaxsugar.de/posts/omnetpp-sim-evaluation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 May 2017 16:57:42 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://syntaxsugar.de/posts/omnetpp-sim-evaluation/</guid>
      <description>OMNeT++ network simulator allows for extensive and modular simulation of network scenarios. When simulation concept, implementation, configuration and running are said and done, the evaluation is the next step. Some built-in functionalities of the IDE allow for an idea on how the network performed. This was cumbersone for me personally, and I prefer to evaluate the numerical scalar result values in MATLAB anyway.
When you run a large number of simulations, then you don&amp;rsquo;t want to open each file in the IDE, select the relevant entries and export them to a .</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Implementing D2D mode selection in OMNeT&#43;&#43;/SIMUlte</title>
      <link>https://syntaxsugar.de/posts/omnetpp-d2d-mode-selection/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 May 2017 16:41:12 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://syntaxsugar.de/posts/omnetpp-d2d-mode-selection/</guid>
      <description>Device2Device (D2D) Mode Selection is the process of deciding whether a user device should communicate directly (D2D Mode) or via the eNodeB base station (Infrastructure Mode). A number of metrics can be taken into account for this decision, such as the interference generated that will affect other devices or the expected datarate of each mode. Once a researcher has come up with an idea, they will want to evaluate it. Using the OMNeT++ network simulator as a starting point, and adding the SIMUlte framework on top enables one to simulate LTE networks.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Implementing an LTE resource scheduler in OMNeT&#43;&#43;/SIMUlte</title>
      <link>https://syntaxsugar.de/posts/omnetpp-scheduler/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 May 2017 15:59:19 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://syntaxsugar.de/posts/omnetpp-scheduler/</guid>
      <description>SIMUlte is an extension framework for the network simulator OMNeT++. It enables simulations of LTE telecommunications.
In this context, resource scheduling is the problem of allocating transmission resources residing in the dimensions of time and of frequency band to user devices. A resource block can be depicted like this:
There are a number of optimization targets we would like to meet:
 system throughput: we want to push out as much data as possible fairness: we want all devices to be able to push out data power efficiency: we want to use as little power as possible  So in the end, resource scheduling boils down to a complex optimization problem.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to safely SSH into your own computer</title>
      <link>https://syntaxsugar.de/posts/safe-ssh-to-own-computer/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Mar 2017 20:01:49 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://syntaxsugar.de/posts/safe-ssh-to-own-computer/</guid>
      <description>I came across a situation where I had to ssh into my personal computer from a remote server. Most of the time, you don&amp;rsquo;t want to do this. There&amp;rsquo;s botnets and other evil-doers out there that try to break into easily accessible machines, and a password-protected SSH connection is easily broken into.
So don&amp;rsquo;t do this unless you really need to!
Okay, so you really need to. What do we need to do?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reading module and simulation parameters in OMNeT&#43;&#43;</title>
      <link>https://syntaxsugar.de/posts/omnetpp-reading-parameters/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Mar 2017 16:43:13 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://syntaxsugar.de/posts/omnetpp-reading-parameters/</guid>
      <description>I had a hard time figuring out how to access general simulation parameters such as the maximum simulation time max-sim-time at runtime from whatever module needs it.
For modules it is rather straightforward. From any cModule object, there&amp;rsquo;s a par(const char* parname) function. Say you&amp;rsquo;re writing a module named OmniscientEntity (as I did), and it is defined in OmniscientEntity.ned as this:
simple OmniscientEntity { parameters: // Used for CQI computation. Copy over from your channel.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Finding equidistant points on a circle</title>
      <link>https://syntaxsugar.de/posts/equidistant-points-on-circle/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Mar 2017 11:34:07 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://syntaxsugar.de/posts/equidistant-points-on-circle/</guid>
      <description>We know that every circle has \(360\degree = 2\pi\). It&amp;rsquo;s what makes them round.
How can we find the (x,y) positions of n that are evenly distributed on a circle?
Trigonometry to the rescue! All points on a circle are equidistant to the circle&amp;rsquo;s center. All we need to do is go around the circle evenly so that we arrive where we started after n steps.
For this, we put each point at an angle \(\theta\) that goes from 360/n to 360 evenly in n steps:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lexicographical index calculation</title>
      <link>https://syntaxsugar.de/posts/lexicographical-index/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Mar 2017 14:21:39 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://syntaxsugar.de/posts/lexicographical-index/</guid>
      <description>Building upon the idea of word frequency vectors, when implementing the idea in a language of your choice, you might encounter the problem of instantiating a container that is going to store the observed frequencies. In an efficient implementation you could instantiate such a container that holds the right number of items, which is \(\left| \sum_{language} \right| ^n\), e.g. for DNA the alphabet is \(\sum_{DNA}=\{A,C,T,G\}\). \(n\) is the word length for which you&amp;rsquo;re finding the frequency vector.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Word frequency vectors and their uses</title>
      <link>https://syntaxsugar.de/posts/word-frequency-vectors/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Mar 2017 18:45:50 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://syntaxsugar.de/posts/word-frequency-vectors/</guid>
      <description>During some work with a Bioinformatics group at the University of Göttingen, we would use word frequency vectors to determine evolutionary distances between DNA or Protein sequences.
A DNA sequence, when saved digitally, is nothing more than a string of characters. Each one corresponds to one of the four possible nucleotides. You could call this DNA&amp;rsquo;s alphabet \(\sum_{DNA}=\{A,C,T,G\}\). A chain of these nucleotides makes up the structure of a DNA strand.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Multi-domain nginx configuration</title>
      <link>https://syntaxsugar.de/posts/nginx/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Mar 2017 20:21:28 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://syntaxsugar.de/posts/nginx/</guid>
      <description>nginx is an open-source HTTP server.
Let&amp;rsquo;s say you&amp;rsquo;re running a server with nginx and you have two domains domain1.com and domain2.com. You also have the HTML of two websites sitting at ~/web/domain1.com/ and ~/web/domain2.com/. And now, of course, you want visitors that go to domain1.com to be directed to the website at ~/web/domain1.com/ and in an analog way for the other domain.
For this you make the sites available by creating their configuration files</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>