<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Simulte on Syntax Sugar</title>
    <link>https://syntaxsugar.de/tags/simulte/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Simulte on Syntax Sugar</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 May 2017 16:41:12 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://syntaxsugar.de/tags/simulte/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Implementing D2D mode selection in OMNeT&#43;&#43;/SIMUlte</title>
      <link>https://syntaxsugar.de/posts/omnetpp-d2d-mode-selection/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 May 2017 16:41:12 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://syntaxsugar.de/posts/omnetpp-d2d-mode-selection/</guid>
      <description>Device2Device (D2D) Mode Selection is the process of deciding whether a user device should communicate directly (D2D Mode) or via the eNodeB base station (Infrastructure Mode). A number of metrics can be taken into account for this decision, such as the interference generated that will affect other devices or the expected datarate of each mode. Once a researcher has come up with an idea, they will want to evaluate it. Using the OMNeT++ network simulator as a starting point, and adding the SIMUlte framework on top enables one to simulate LTE networks.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Implementing an LTE resource scheduler in OMNeT&#43;&#43;/SIMUlte</title>
      <link>https://syntaxsugar.de/posts/omnetpp-scheduler/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 May 2017 15:59:19 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://syntaxsugar.de/posts/omnetpp-scheduler/</guid>
      <description>SIMUlte is an extension framework for the network simulator OMNeT++. It enables simulations of LTE telecommunications.
In this context, resource scheduling is the problem of allocating transmission resources residing in the dimensions of time and of frequency band to user devices. A resource block can be depicted like this:
There are a number of optimization targets we would like to meet:
 system throughput: we want to push out as much data as possible fairness: we want all devices to be able to push out data power efficiency: we want to use as little power as possible  So in the end, resource scheduling boils down to a complex optimization problem.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>